Register of the G. Warren Nutter papers
Hoover Institution Archives
G. Warren Nutter papers
1956-1978
81077
Hoover Institution Archives
4 manuscript boxes, 1 oversize box 3.2 linear feet
Writings and memoranda relating to the calculation of industrial growth in the Soviet Union and to miscellaneous aspects of American defense policy. Includes drafts of G. Warren Nutter's book, Growth of Industrial Production in the Soviet Union (1962). Digital copies of select records also available at https://digitalcollections.hoover.org.
Nutter, G. Warren
Access
Collection is open for research. Digital copies of select records also available at https://digitalcollections.hoover.org.
The Hoover Institution Archives only allows access to copies of audiovisual items, computer media, and digital files. To listen to sound recordings or to view videos, films, or digital files during your visit, please contact the Archives at least two working days before your arrival. We will then advise you of the accessibility of the material you wish to see or hear. Please note that not all material is immediately accessible.
Acquisition Information
Acquired by the Hoover Institution Archives in 1981.
Accruals
Materials may have been added to the collection since this finding aid was prepared. To determine if this has occurred, find the collection in Stanford University's online catalog at http://searchworks.stanford.edu/. Materials have been added to the collection if the number of boxes listed in the online catalog is larger than the number of boxes listed in this finding aid.
Alternate Forms Available
Digital copies of select records also available at https://digitalcollections.hoover.org.
Related Collections
Mont Pèlerin Society records, Hoover Institution Archives Gordon Tullock papers, Hoover Institution Archives
Location of Originals
Originals in possession of Eugene Zaleski.
Biographical Note
1923 Born, Topeka, Kansas
1944 B.A., University of Chicago
1946-1947 Instructor, Lawrence College, Appleton, Wisconsin
1948 M.A., University of Chicago
1949 Ph.D., University of Chicago
1949-1956 Assistant professor of economics, Yale University
1955-1967 Research staff member, National Bureau of Economic Research
1957-1967 Associate director, Thomas Jefferson Center for Political Economy
1958-1958 Associate professor, University of Virginia, Charlottesville
1958-1979 Professor, University of Virginia, Charlottesville
1962 Author, Growth of Industrial Production in the Soviet Union
1967-1976 Director, Thomas Jefferson Center for Political Economy
1969 Author, Enterprise Monopoly in the United States, 1899-1958, with Henry Adler Einhorn
1969-1973 Assistant secretary of defense for international security affairs, United States Department of Defense
1976-1979 Member, International Studies Program, Hoover Institution
1979 Died
Scope and Content of Collection
The papers of G. Warren Nutter, which consist largely of photocopies, relate to the calculation of industrial growth in the Soviet Union and to miscellaneous aspects of American defense policy. The Writings series includes drafts of Growth of Industrial Production in the Soviet Union and related statistical abstracts. The Declassified U.S. Government Records series contains formerly security-classified records and interfiled unclassified records relating to Southeast Asia, the Vietnam War, and the Prisoner of War/Missing in Action Task Force, as well as notes from meetings with Secretary of Defense staff, Secretary of Defense/International Security Affairs, and the Chairman of the Joint Chiefs of Staff and slides for a Department of Defense conference presentation.
Economists.; Soviet Union--Economic conditions.; Soviet Union--Industries.; United States--Defenses.; United States--Military policy.
- Writings, 1956-1966 (Boxes 1-3)
  Scope and Contents note
  Includes drafts of Growth of Industrial Production in the Soviet Union and related materials, such as statistical abstracts. Arranged chronologically.
  - Statistical Abstract of Industrial Output in the Soviet Union, 1913-1955, 1956-1957 (Box 1)
    - Part 1, 1956 (Box-folder 1: 1-2)
    - Part 2, 1956 (Box-folder 1: 3)
    - Part 3, 1956 (Box-folder 1: 4)
    - Part 4, 1956 (Box-folder 1: 5)
    - Part 5, 1956 (Box-folder 1: 6)
    - Supplement, 1957 (Box-folder 1: 7)
  - Growth of Industrial Production in the Soviet Union, 1958-1960 (Boxes 2-3)
    Previously titled Industrial Output in the Soviet Union.
    - Draft, 1958 (Box-folder 2: 1-5)
    - Draft, 1960 (Box-folder 2: 6)
    - Draft (cont'd.), 1960 (Box-folder 3: 1-3)
  - "Sur la measure de la croissance economique,", 1965 (Box-folder 3: 4)
  - "Comments on the Estimates of Value and Structure of Soviet Industrial Production of Professor G. Warren Nutter,", 1966 (Box-folder 3: 5)
    Includes tables.
- Declassified U.S. Government Records, 1961-1978 (Reading room workstation, Boxes 3-5)
  Formerly security-classified records of the U.S. government, released in full or in part. Includes some interfiled, unclassified government records. Arranged chronologically by date of release by Hoover.
  - 2010 release of records, 1969-1978 (Reading room workstation)
    Records relating chiefly to Southeast Asia, the Vietnam War, and the Prisoner of War/Missing in Action Task Force. Also includes records relating to defense matters in other parts of the world and administrative matters. Available as PDF files. Arranged chronologically by date of creation.
  - 2011 June release of records, 1961-1973 (Boxes 3-4)
    Unclassified records, chiefly relating to meetings with Secretary of Defense staff, Secretary of Defense/International Security Affairs, and the Chairman of the Joint Chiefs of Staff. Also includes records relating to policy plans, administrative matters, and other subjects. Arranged by file number, name of meeting, or subject.
    - List of classified speeches of G. Warren Nutter, 1969-1972 (Box-folder 3: 6)
    - List of classified congressional statements of G. Warren Nutter, 1969-1972 (Box-folder 3: 7)
    - Index of classified materials, stewardship report, 1973 (Box-folder 3: 8)
    - File 10, Europe and NATO, 1971 (Box-folder 3: 9)
    - File 12, inter-American affairs, 1971 (Box-folder 3: 10)
    - File 13, foreign military rights affairs, 1972 (Box-folder 3: 11)
    - File 14, strategic trade and disclosure, 1969-1971 (Box-folder 3: 12)
    - File 15, East Asia-Pacific, undated (Box-folder 3: 13)
    - File 17, Prisoner of War Task Force, 1972 (Box-folder 3: 14)
    - File 18, Defense Security Assistance Agency, 1961-1973 (Box-folder 3: 15)
    - File 19, PDASD (Principal Deputy Assistant Secretary Defense), administration, 1969-1972 (Box-folder 3: 16)
    - File 20, principal assistant, 1970-1972 (Box-folder 3: 17)
    - CJCS (Chairman for Joint Chiefs of Staff) meeting notes, 1970-1972 (Box-folder 4: 1-3)
    - NSSM (National Security Study memoranda), 1969 (Box-folder 4: 4)
    - Policy plans (Box 4)
      - Volume 1, organization and relationships, 1969-1972 (Box-folder 4: 5)
      - Volume 2, defense economic affairs, 1972 (Box-folder 4: 6)
      - Volume 5, miscellaneous significant issues, part 1, undated (Box-folder 4: 7)
      - Volume 6, miscellaneous significant issues, part 2, 1972 (Box-folder 4: 8)
      - Volume 7, mutual balanced force reductions, 1972 (Box-folder 4: 9)
      - Volume 8, economic aspects of Vietnamization, 1970-1972 (Box-folder 4: 10)
    - Secretary of Defense staff meeting notes, 1971-1973 (Box-folder 4: 11-14)
    - Secretary of Defense/ISA (International Security Affairs) meeting notes, 1969-1973 (Box-folder 4: 15-19)
  - 2016 March release of records, 1969 (Box 5)
    Department of Defense Management Conference (13 December 1969) slides for a presentation titled "The World-Wide Political-Military Situation."